perfect
uh
[Music]
hello everybody good evening and good
day welcome to episode 55 of the ask a
budget show
another weekend another series of shows
so
i hope you're all doing well i hope
you're doing great
let us see who all is there with us i
can see ankit mishra varad yoshi
amandeep
sagar bhanu prakash jai dikshit
aaron
hello everybody great to see you all
great to see you all
so what shall we talk about what shall
we discuss as always you ask the
questions i answer your questions let's
see what questions are already here let
us take a look
let us take a look at the questions
okay
[Laughter]
gayatri says there's already one dislike
even before the video started
i think i think it's the case is that
they don't dislike me they dislike all
of us that's why before it started
they've disliked the video
it's okay go ahead dislike it
all right what else
um
let us see some interesting questions i
as always i'm gonna take questions that
i haven't
taken up
before
so so so so so what shall we what shall
we pick up what shall we pick up
uh
okay let's start with this question
vinay mundra asks thought or thoughts on
indian jewry
not allowing the film udam singh for
oscars saying it's
anti-british hate
yeah this this tells us about the mental
colonization of
that still
permeates india especially the
establishment
i don't know who are the members of this
jury they typically are people who are
associated with bollywood
eminent people etc and our eminent
people are all anglophiles
they all love the west they are all
indebted to the west and the
neheruvian and so on establishment for
whatever they have achieved and whatever
their status and position in society is
and therefore they are very much
pro
pro west pro all that and they
and therefore they feel that india needs
to be needs to stay the same
differential to the west differential to
the british raj
thankful to the british for everything
they have apparently done for us
civilizing us uplift uplifting us from
our backwardness and so on and so forth
and apparently if we
portray history as it really happened
then it is
it is anti-british hate
so i think it is regrettable it is it is
deplorable
that
a film has been
rejected based on
politics
rather than on the quality of the movie
see movies films cinema is
supposed to depict
society as it exists and history as it
happened
there are i mean cinema traditionally
has taken up very
difficult issues at times
controversial issues
and that is the job of cinema to explore
these issues and portray them
in a in a manner that can be processed
by society
i mean uh i i can
think of the example of uh quentin
tarantino's movie in glorious bastards
in which which is a historical
revisionist story in which
in which uh hitler and the nazis are all
killed
by a band of jews i think in france
somewhere in france
so it's it's an alternative history
movie
and there's a lot of violence and all
that so so should we construe that to be
anti-german hate
is that does that movie depict
clearly it does not
the the germans especially not not the
germans as such but the nazis were
horrible people
and what's wrong in saying that they
were horrible similarly the british what
they did in india was horrible it was it
was inhuman it was barbaric
it was deplorable
more than 100 million indians died
during the british occupation of india
winston churchill was a brute of a
person
barbarian hindu phobe
what he did in india was nothing short
of genocide crimes against humanity
the
artificial famine that he engineered in
bengal
the according to the british records
about two to three to four million
indians died which is absolute nonsense
we have to multiply that by at least a
figure of two i think the actual figure
would be closer to 10 million indians
who died during that artificially
engineered famine
so it is clear that the british
perpetrated horrific atrocities in india
and to claim that an indian movie
uh
is is a representative of anti-british
hate
is ridiculous
so i think it is deplorable what the
so-called jury has done
and we need to reform these
institutions of ours which are still
deeply deeply colonial they still carry
the white man's burden
their
their members act as if they are
honorable
white men honorable british
so this needs to change india needs to
rediscover its
its sense of self-respect and
yeah changes need to happen so this is
very unfortunate what's happened and
it's good that you bring this up
okay karthik srinivas says can
blockchain eliminate corruption
completely
what are all the changes we can witness
from the implementation of blockchain
that's an interesting question i don't
think blockchain can eliminate
corruption completely
so blockchain is a new technology you
have the ledger in which we have a
permanent record of whatever happens so
on i'm not going to explain what that is
in detail right now because that's a
totally different topic it'll take time
to explain that in in a in a proper
manner the thing is that many people
claim that blockchain is going to
ensure complete transparency of
transactions and eliminate corruption
and so on so forth
i disagree
let's say you have complete transparency
of
transactions and the complete proper
record of what happened and yet if a
country is corrupt either the country
can ban blockchain
or even if blockchain is allowed
if the institutions don't work
then what's the what's the point if
there is some sort of fraud for instance
let's say a terrorist uses
blockchain to transfer funds to hidden
operatives within the country it's going
to happen anyway
right so terrorism can can actually
proliferate using something like
blockchain because it it bypasses all
government controls
secondly even
certain corrupt individuals or
organizations may actually indulge in
corrupt practices uh transfer of money
transfer of bribes via blockchain and if
the let's say the country
has good laws to to take care of this to
to eliminate corruption and so on but if
the laws aren't implemented then those
laws are useless
if you have a pendency of 5 million
cases in front of the judiciary then by
the time they come to dealing with your
case 30 40 years would have elapsed
and justice delayed is justice denied
so to eliminate corruption you need
political will
you need on a complete overhaul of the
institutions and the processes
the policing mechanisms the judiciary
the laws i mean you can have the best
laws in the country
but if your judiciary
is unable to function for whatever
reason
then those laws are pointless and you
may have the best laws in the country
but if the
law enforcement agencies are unwilling
or unable to enforce the laws then again
those laws are
pointless
so so it is not blockchain that will
eliminate corruption
it is reforms
of india's institutions
india's
failing decrepit
colonial institutions it is that reform
is those reforms whenever they happen
someday in the future hopefully it is
that
that will eliminate corruption it is
political will that will eliminate
corruption today you have corruption
throughout the length and the breadth of
india the country practically runs on
corruption the government governance
system at the lowest levels
in many places i'm not saying everywhere
okay don't get me wrong
i'm i'm not saying everywhere but in
many parts of the country you have
significant corruption at the lowest
levels
and so so
that's because everyone knows about it
and no and and the system not only
tolerates it the system encourages it
so no matter how how much technology you
bring in blockchain or anything else
as long as the system
um
the system is as long as the system is
complicit in corruption nothing can
change so it's political will where is
india's
war against corruption
where is it
when that happens you will have freedom
from corruption not blockchain can't
really do much about it
right let's take some more interesting
question
right satoru gojo says where um
how did this idea of string theory come
is there any alternative to it because
many scientists disproved it
so i think uh
string theory is a response to the
problem of gravitation
uh
we need to find a way of uh
see the thing is this when we have a
very successful theory of gravitation
it's called general relativity the
general theory of relativity four
dimensional space time
mass curves space time and the curvature
of space time tells mass how to move
that sort of thing so it's a very
extremely successful theory it works
brilliantly and yet it is a flawed
theory we know that because at the ultra
microscopic scale it blows up the
einstein equations blow up they give up
they give rise to singularities they
throw up infinities and whenever you
have an infinity you whenever you have a
singularity it tells you there's
something wrong with the equations
you are getting a division by zero which
is unphysical
and therefore these infinities the
singularities are
uh a pointer to the fact that there is a
flaw in general relativity you we are
unable to reconcile general relativity
and quantum mechanics and quantum field
theory
so you are
the equations of general relativity
breakdown in
uh at the smallest levels
and quantum physics doesn't work in
curved space time so that's what's
happening and that is the reason why
people started thinking
physicists started looking for
alternatives for new approaches to
solving this problem
now we already had theories in extra
dimensions we had kalooza client theory
which is quite old actually it threw up
very interesting results
so physicists
and and we know that our theories are
approximate theories for instance we
treat particles as points
zero dimensional points which is
unphysical because particles no matter
how small they may be in the quantum
realm they still are physical
objects physical entities and they would
occupy
some volume of space
and therefore to treat them as particles
as as a point
particles is actually unphysical and
therefore
physicists decided to try a new approach
to to start with the fundamental unit of
of
of the material universe as being a
one-dimensional vibrating string
and they thought let's try to construct
a particle physics
out of this
and that was the beginning of string
theory so instead of zero dimensional
points we have one dimensional strings
strings that vibrate strings that could
could loop around each other the strings
that could become circles and the
frequency of vibration gives rise to
certain properties and so on i'm not
going to the details but that
essentially is the idea of string theory
now to make this theory work
to to to create a cohesive coherent
theory of
out of this
a proper model
of the world of the universe they had to
extend this into 11 dimensions i think
10 11 13 i mean there's a number of
different flavors and versions of the
string theory and yet it has not worked
string theory has been around for i
think almost half a century or or more
if i'm not mistaken and yet it has not
produced a single
testable prediction thus far
and if a theory is unable to produce a
single prediction that can actually be
tested then the theory is worthless
right and the theory this string theory
throws up this uh
the string theory landscape 10 raised to
500 different possible universes that's
the which is the string theory
multiverse
and
so the main problem with string theory
is that it is unable to make a single
testable prediction
and that is the biggest failure of
string theory a theory has
a theory has to
be able to produce
predictions that can be tested
and that is why
it is increasingly
obvious that this is a failed theory the
mathematics is beautiful the mathematics
is extremely complex
it's very it's it's like you're doing
mathematics instead of physics you claim
that you're physicists but you're just
producing equations you're you're
playing with equations producing
extremely complicated mathematical
results and calling it physics
and today you if you look at the
various journals if you look at the
physics preprint archive and so on you
will find dozens of new papers being
published every day but where are we
progressing are we progressing anywhere
is there any new progress being done in
physics no none
and therefore
it is clear that string theory has
failed and yet the major funding
that is available in the west especially
in the united states is all in the field
of string theory
all the academic departments in physics
departments in physics are filled with
string theories when i when i say
physics i mean theoretical physics so
they're all staffed by by string
theorists it's like a mafia which has
taken over physics and they are
unwilling to let go because their entire
livelihood depends on it
and that's the big problem right now
that's why physics is unable to progress
people are unwilling to look at
different solute different uh ideas
and uh people who try to look at
different ideas of ideas that are
outside of string theory get
marginalized their work isn't pop is
rejected it is not published and so on
so that's the problem so alternatives to
string theory i mean
there are plenty of alternatives but
there is no funding available to pursue
these alternatives and that's why
uh it's it's it's not really working out
i i would say that we need to look at
physics in three plus one dimensions
four dimensions at most
we need to uh rethink our approach
try to
re-simplify things instead of over
complicating things the way
they have been done in spring theory we
need to
uh take a variety of different
approaches i'm not i'll not go into what
approaches but there are plenty
available so it's it's high time we dump
this failed theory
and and look at novel approaches
approaches in four dimensions not not 11
dimensions or whatever the hell that is
right
so that is what needs to happen it was a
good idea but it's not produced any
results so it needs to be
discarded at least for the time being
right
good question let us
take some more questions as always
um
try to claim that all our ancient
astronomy mathematics alchemy technology
philosophy etc has been derived from the
greeks is it true it is entirely
completely 100
untrue it is false
indian civilization predates the greek
civilization by 7 000 years at least
so the earliest evidence that we have of
greek civilization is about
about three and a half three thousand
three and a half thousand years from
before today
okay if you want to be charitable let's
say four thousand years before today
around 2000 bce but there is there is
the greek pre-history that's not really
greek civilization
the actual greek civilization the
flowering of the city states etc
happened about two and a half thousand
or so years ago
so that is greek civilization india's
civilization predates that by thousands
of years
if you look at when the greeks came to
india during the time of alexander the
robber and the seleucus nicator they
discovered that the indians us our
ancestors had a system a calendar
that dated back to around 6000 something
bce which is eight and a half thousand
years before today
that is how deep how old our reckoning
was of time
we had been keeping records since
around six and a half thousand bce
that's how our that's how old our memory
was our recorded memories
were right
so the greeks where were infants
compared the greek civilization was was
an
infantile civilization compared to
indian civilization
the earliest recorded
the earliest record of a supernova
is from about 5 000 years before today
or something like that in north india
and kashmir
and so on so we have been doing uh
recording astronomical events for
thousands of years
we have a very ancient philosophical and
mathematical edition astronomical
tradition
uh you go back 5000 years our technology
was the most advanced in the world the
uh saraswati hindu civilization
is in the phase of our civilization if
you look at the cities the the city
planning the town planning the grid
system the drainage system the multi
storage buildings the
standardization of weights and measures
the hydro engineering the harbors and so
on and so forth it's incredibly advanced
for the time the cities were better
planned better organized than today's
modern indian cities the drainage
systems then
five thousand years before today were
better than today's drainage systems and
so on
and and so on right so so this these
claims are are
desperate euro-centric claims
the europeans realized about
a few centuries ago that they there's
they were no match
to india's civilization to the antiquity
and depth and profundity of india's
civilization
so therefore they invented these claims
because uh the the so-called western
civilization whatever the hell that is
is believe it they claim that it's its
origin is rome and greece and
and uh judea
and egypt
and and
mesopotamia so that is the
origin of of the so-called western
civilization and therefore they want to
attribute everything to that region to
either to egypt or to the jews judea
or to greece or to rome
that's it and they want to deny that
india had
was better than any of these
other
empires or so-called civilizations and
that's why they make these claims and
our professors our history writers
our so-called eminent historians and so
on they blindly ape these western claims
and that's why we are taught all these
nonsense so we need to de-program our
minds
and realize that our civilization is the
india is the mother of civilization
india is the true cradle of civilization
everything sprang from here before it
went elsewhere
right some more questions i have
answered some questions before
love deep sings says how can russia be a
strategic partner in war with china for
india well i don't know if there's going
to be a war there could be a possibility
of what in the next year or so perhaps
possibly china's economy is floundering
china is desperate and reaching
see when your economy is floundering
when you're not doing well
that's when you want to
that's when your leaders become more
ambitious they want to
reach for something before it's on
before it's no longer available and it
is this desperation that often
leads
to
to rash decisions
and to war so as we speak right now
there is this buildup of troops on
india's northern border with tibet which
is currently occupied by china right now
temporarily
so the chinese are amassing troops and
equipment etc
in tibet
on the border with india and india is
also responding in kind and there is a
very tense situation going on right now
what is china's intention we don't know
yet but we are clearly capable of
responding
uh i think we will be stalking our
brahmos missiles right now in case the
chinese try something that's going to be
problematic for them now what is
russia's role in this right now there's
no role
right right now there is no role for
russia in this the russians are kind of
trying to
take a neutral stance when it comes to
china and india this relationship
they're trying to keep an equidistant
stance they have supplied
the s 400
missile system to the chinese but they
are also supplying the same thing to us
i'm sure the chinese are not very
pleased about this at all and yet the
russians are doing it so they are arming
india india and china with the same
uh missile system which is an
extraordinarily good and powerful
missile system
so
but the russians are
in a quasi kind of alliance with china
to some extent they also have nuclear
missiles pointed at china
they certainly don't trust china but
they are currently in
some kind of alliance with china against
the west because the west is very much
anti-russia also anti-china so for the
time being their interests converge to
some extent and that's why they're
working together
but the russians also know that in the
long run the chinese are a very big
threat to russia
and therefore they will also want to
maintain good relations with india
because india is the only
nation state in asia that can
possibly
uh counterbalance china or pose a
genuine threat to china there is no
other nation in asia
that can pose a threat to china the way
india can india has the
potential to pose
a significant and and genuine threat to
china if india's economy keeps growing
for the next 10 years then india's
military might will also grow
correspondingly proportionately
so if india is able to avoid conflict
for the next 10 years then it's going to
be a very significant challenger to
china
it's a question of 10 years and
sustained growth
once india's economy crosses the 10
trillion dollar mark
then
well that's what we need to go for
that's what we need to achieve at the
earliest and we have taken significant
strides in the direction
i mean we
may not realize it but our economy has
been transformed in the past five years
or so
i mean do you realize how easy it is to
do online transactions now with your
phone using upi
uh even i i hear even street vendors and
vegetable sellers etc and small shop
owners are using uh these uh
these paytm and gpa and whatnot right
you can you can buy vegetables through
this thing it wasn't it was never
you could not even dream of that five
years ago
so india has exceeded even china in
online transactions per month that is a
fantastic thing i think the gst has also
opened up india to to
i mean earlier you had all these
barriers to trade
to to transport goods and supplies
across india so that has disappeared now
even though the gst needs to further be
reformed and yet it is a it is a very
significant step in the right direction
and so on and so forth so so india's
economy is now
going to really take off
in the next five ten years so that's
what india needs to aim for india needs
to sustain
this growth
anyhow
you elect the wrong people it's all
gonna go
backwards so remember these guys and
girls so that's what needs to happen and
that's why the chinese are currently
worried their economy is grinding down
our economy is
slowly but steadily
growing
so russia is going to be watching this
russia is watching this very closely
they will look out for their own
interests so we cannot expect russia to
be an overt partner
in case india goes to war with china
but it is certainly in russia's
long-term interests to be on india's
side so it's an interesting situation
right now
uh most likely there won't be any war if
there is a war it could happen in the
northern border a short sharp war the
chinese may try to grab some more
territory
like in 1962 i think they will if they
do that it's gonna be a disaster for
them
and so on so let's let's wait and watch
the situation is currently quite fluid
we don't know what's going to happen
we could have a war possibly
not a major war but a localized
short sharp war like the cargill war
that sort of thing is certainly possible
maybe in the next few months
maybe before winter sets in
maybe in the next year or so i don't
know let's see it all depends on the
chinese
india won't initiate a war like that
india won't initiate a war but if the
chinese do initiate it we will be able
to respond
properly and teach them a lesson
so
let's see
pratik says can we say that lord hanuman
was of homo erectus race and the
ramayana era was a coexistence between
homo erectus and homo sapiens no we have
absolutely no evidence
that supports such a claim
i think homo erectus died out at least a
hundred thousand years before today
and we know that the out of africa
migration happened
about
70 75 000 years before today
right
and therefore it is uh very hard to
imagine a coexistence of homo sapiens
and homo erectus i am not ruling it out
completely it is certainly
possible if new evidence emerges we may
get a different kind of idea of what
happened but from the best evidence that
we have right now
it appears that there was
that the coexistence of homo sapiens and
homo erectus may have been very unlikely
but of course if mo if new evidence
turns up that we may have to revise this
understanding
now i don't think the ramayana era was
like
70 80 90 100 000 years ago i do not
believe that at all
it's it's simply not possible the
ramayana uh the events of the ramayana
most likely happened sometime in the
last 1000 10 000 years
uh i think it's quite a reach of the
imagination to say it happened 10 or 12
or 50 000 years ago most likely within
the last 10 000 years
uh
so we still don't know when it happened
there are all kinds of competing claims
i know what you guys are gonna comment
now but you know what nothing is proven
thus far
none of the claims has been
independently verified or corroborated
and therefore i'm not going to
say that this claim is correct or that
claim is correct
my gut feeling is that it is somewhere
in the past 10 000 years cannot be
before that i i just simply
i mean it doesn't make any sense right
there is something called glottal
chronology
the rate of change of languages
now we know that the sanskrit language
has changed if you look at the sanskrit
language that is
uh
that you see in the rig veda and if you
look at the kind of sanskrit that was
spoken in the atharva veda you can see
differences you can see that the
language language has changed certain
words
have gone out of usage new words have
turned up in the rig veda the word for
night
is not ratri it is nakta
the old rigvedic sanskrit word for night
was nakta
and in the atharva veda
their word for night is ratri the word
has gone out of existence
so languages
change if the ramayana happened 12 15
000 years ago then how come it was
written in proper sanskrit
how is it even possible
and clearly we know that the ramayana
comes after the rigveda
and we and the best
i mean
tentatively one would imagine that the
rig weather was written sometime around
6000 or bce or somewhere around that
period because that's when the saraswati
was in its prime
and therefore
if the ramayana happened some four five
six thousand years ago
or thereabouts then there is no chance
of homo erectus being around in the
indian subcontinent at the time
and therefore these the speculations
that uh many people make are
unfortunately
are not consistent with the evidence
that we have at hand right and therefore
i would like to say that uh
one cannot say that lord roman was was
of whichever other species
and so on right so we have to examine
the evidence that we have at hand
and formulate our theories
based on that evidence
right that's all i would like to say
about this so good question pratik
sagnik banerjee says why is the distant
universe so homogeneous when the big
bang theory seems to predict
larger measurable and isotropics of the
night sky than those observed are you
sure what you know what you're asking
okay maybe you do
so here's the thing
the universe is not
completely homogeneous
right
i don't know what
predictions of larger measurable
you're referring to
here's the thing you see when um
when we actually observe when we
actually map
the cosmic microwave background
radiation across the universe
we do
observe
an isotropism across the universe
right
so this is
something that is symptomatic
of quantum fluctuations that happened in
the very very
early universe right after the big bang
quantum fluctuations are something that
arises out of quantum field theory space
time
space itself even the vacuum of space is
not empty it's filled with this quantum
fluctuations virtual particles coming in
and out of existence
arising and annihilating each other and
so on so you have quantum fluctuations
happening in the vacuum of space in the
early very early universe these quantum
fluctuations would have led to over
densities localized over densities in
space which could have seeded primordial
black holes
which could then have eventually over
time
become the seeds of supermassive black
holes that are the the center of
galaxies
so the very early universe was not
homogeneous
it had
regions of over densities seeded by
quantum fluctuations and that's the
result of that is visible in the night
sky in in the
in the map of the cosmic microwave
background redefine so uh there was this
uh this uh
satellite called a w map that was
that was uh launched i don't know
20 30 years ago 1980s 1990s thereabouts
i don't remember when so it was the
first experiment that mapped the cosmic
microwave microwave background radiation
that you see in the universe and it
showed these n isotropies these regions
where you had non-homogeneous
distribution of
cmbr the temperature the temperature
fluctuations and all that
then recently about 10 years ago the
planck satellite the planck experiment
was launched which gave us a better view
of it the resolution was inc was
improved and you saw that these
anisotropies are very very very
prevalent across
the universe these are very small
differences in the temperature and yet
they are they are very much visible they
are very much measurable
and
it also appears that the universe is not
completely homogeneous homogeneous means
whichever direction you look at it an
isotropic means whichever direction you
look at it look at the universe and
isotropy means that it is the same so we
have an isotropist and the universe may
not even be completely homogeneous
you look in one direction you look in a
different direction there may be some
differences in the density of of matter
and so on so you know what right now we
are in our infancy when it comes to
observational astrophysics astronomy etc
our instruments are very primitive
as our instruments get better better
we'll be able to peer deeper into the
night sky into the universe and we will
be able to see the universe in a better
resolution when you're watching a video
if you're watching the video in 480p
it is quite
uh
it is quite granular
it's quite noisy now if you if you
change the resolution to 720p it gets
better yeah now you can see more details
if you change the resolution to 1080p
hd resolution it gets even better so
this broadcast this telecast this live
stream is in hd 1080p
so you will be able to see significant
details here
if i
uh if we change it even further to 4k
you will see even more details and
that's the same with our astronomical
instruments
initially with the with the wmap
experiment you were able to see only
fuzzy details now the planck experiment
has given us a better resolution and you
can see more details in the future we
will be able to see even more so as we
get more data
we will get a better understanding of
how the universe is right now from what
we see it is a little early
to to make to draw conclusions about how
the universe is right so
our knowledge is going to keep changing
it's going to keep
uh improving as we get more information
we will be able to understand the
universe better but we certainly have an
isotropy when we certainly have
in homogeneitis in the universe
all right let's move on to the next
question
all right let's see some more let's see
some more questions
costume shoe classes according to you
who will be the top five super powers
on the basis of military and economic
strength and where does india stand in
the list by 2025 2025 is day after
tomorrow more or less so the top five so
see
what is the definition of the term
superpower
a superpower is a nation
that can
that has a global reach and a global
influence it can
influence events
in any part of the world
at very short notice
so let's say the americans want to bomb
a terrorist ship in
some in the south pacific region
they can most likely have it done in the
next one or two hours if they want any
time
so that's the kind of global reach they
have
they have aircraft carriers throughout
the world they have satellites that map
every part of the world they have
submarines nuclear submarines etc in
various parts of the world they have
army bases on every single continent
except antarctica hopefully antarctica
right
so they have this global reach they have
a network
that is global military network and so
on and so forth so that is the
definition of a superpower
so by that definition the united states
is the only superpower in the world
today the chinese are an aspiring
superpower they want to create that sort
of global
network of power
and influence
right so they are
building towards that but they are far
from reaching that objective there are
only a few military bases
in the indo-pacific region
there's one in djibouti in
eastern africa there are a couple of
bases in pakistan that can be
regarded or construed as
dual use
military naval bases so they are trying
to create a network of ports etc that
can in the future be used for military
purposes
but they are way way way behind
the united states when it comes to the
global network of military bases and
other other things
so the chinese are far behind the us and
yet
if you look at the economic might they
may
catch up with the u.s in the next 10
years or so most likely it will happen
the military power is still way behind
the us
the russians
are a former superpower they had that
kind of ability in the past after the
collapse of the ussr much of that got
destroyed
much of that was fitted away during the
time of mr boris yeltsin
so the russians are a very major
regional power but they have the
greatest
and the largest nuclear arsenal in the
world it's even greater than that of the
us
so these are the top three powers if you
look at the strength of nuclear of the
nuclear arsenal the the russians are
number one the americans are number two
and most likely the chinese are number
three
so those are the top three military
powers
when it comes to smaller
regional powers
one would imagine that india is one of
them the japanese are one of them the
french
are a significant power because they
also have a kind of global
uh power projection capability at least
in the
in the indian ocean because they have
islands that they administer in the
indian ocean they're part of the french
nation
then the french nation state they have
they're called overseas territories or
something there is the island of reynio
in the indian ocean near the
seychelles and
there are some other islands as well i
think in the south pacific
etc
so they have
this sort of
system and that's why they have a
significant naval presence in the indian
ocean so the french are a significant
naval power they have nuclear weapons
they have nuclear submarines that carry
these ballistic missiles
so i would say the top five powers
there's only one superpower but you have
the us as number one china is number two
you the russians is number three because
there's a significant power military if
not economically
then you have powers like the the
the french
india
and japan
maybe the uk but the uk is not really
much of a power actually
and in asia the iranians are up are a
significant power to some extent because
at least they are willing to project
power beyond their borders india is a
massive power but it
thus far
it has
chosen
not to
uh project power
beyond its borders except for one or two
instances like bala coat or the
myanmar uh
surgical strikes
but the way the iranians
operate in other countries
through covert means
through their intelligence networks pies
assassins all that the way the israelis
do it globally
india has thus far chosen not to do that
there must be a good reason for that
maybe it may change in the future let's
wait and watch but i would say that
these are the major powers as of now
2025 is just a couple of years ago so
not much will change by then but by 2030
things
may most likely change significantly
if india's economy keeps growing the way
it should
then india could be a top three power
economically and militarily by 2030.
god's willing
let's see
all right let's
let's see some more
good questions
string theory i answered already
okay i can see lots of new questions let
me take some of these
book recommendation vivek bharath says
which book should i read to get an
introduction to indian philosophy
the thing about book recommendations is
that i i never i can never remember the
right books
you see it's like this i mean people
have commented in the past criticism
that you should at least recommend one
or two books
the thing is that if you read three
books you will remember the three books
if you read three thousand books you
will not remember any of them you
remember the ideas right so that's the
problem i face i cannot remember the
names of the books
all the ideas are there they're all
mixed together
but i am unable to remember specific
names of books but let me recommend one
i think i have a book here somewhere
okay let us recommend this book it's
called philosophies of india
joseph campbell and heinrich zimmer
this may not be the best book it may not
be the best introductory book it's a
massive book
but hey you want book recommendation
here you go here's one
and then there is an even more massive
book which is uh
radhakrishnan's book about indian
book about indian philosophy i don't
know where it is it's somewhere else not
here i've got many other bookshelves
so
here's a couple of book recommendations
go for it sir
right
niladri says
do you not think that it will be
difficult to unite india
in the coming few years well well well
well well india is a very disunited
country it's as if we had a coalition of
smaller countries
every state has its own language
they have it their own political agenda
every state acts as if it is a separate
country
many states act like that especially in
southern india especially in so called
northeast of india we have our own
culture we have our own ways
don't interfere too much
and so on so yeah it is a big challenge
it's because of india's so-called
federal structure they say it's india
strength i say it's india's biggest
weakness a nation state as large as
india a subcontinent-sized nation-state
needs a very strong powerful central
government
which should be able to supersede the
state governments in most matters
pertaining to national
security
and the national interest
and uh
we need a unifying
um
a unifying identity
unfortunately today what we find is that
every community every
religion every state seems to place
their
local
identity above the national identity
my religion comes before the nation
my language comes before the nation
my state
comes before the nation we are a
different kind of people we do things
differently in our state don't impose
this or that on us that's the kind of
nonsense that is prevalent
in certain parts of india
whether it's in northern india
whether it's in southern india
whether it's i mean it's everywhere in
eastern india and so on and so forth
so that is
a legacy of the system our so-called
alleged founding fathers have created
i do not recognize those people as our
fine founding fathers
they are not our founding fathers india
was not founded in 1947
and yet we treat those people as our
founding fathers and we worship their
nonsense whatever they've left behind
for us it is actually extraordinarily
extraordinarily detrimental to india's
national interest and our civilizational
identity
so yes it will be difficult to unite
india in the coming few years like i
have said many times it's a question of
leadership when the right leader emerges
he or she
will
need to have
the willpower the force of character the
force of personality and the force of
will
to unify the country whether the country
likes it or not
that's how it needs to happen
you cannot there this you know the
chinese complain
that no they don't complain
they this at india they laugh at
india they say there's too much
democracy in india look at india perfect
example of too much democracy this is
the reason why democracy is wrong and it
doesn't work you know they have a good
good point there there's too much
democracy in india
democracy means you can say things that
are anti-national in nature you can
you can uh
[Laughter]
you can celebrate pakistan's victory
over india it's funny that people
certain people
are so gleeful when pakistan defeats
india in a sporting sporting encounter
and the same people don't care when
pakistan defeats afghanistan in a
sporting encounter
right
so they are happy only when pakistan
defeats india but when pakistan defeats
new zealand or afghanistan it doesn't
matter to them so it tells you that it's
not about pakistan or any sporting thing
it's just about being anti-india
and being happy when india's big enemy
is able to defeat india once in a
thousand years or so
so yeah we have this sentiment which is
very open
very prevalent
and it is embraced by the liberal media
the so-called liberal media and
various people and various establishment
figures and all that various
intellectuals
and celebrities
and in a nation that tolerates this sort
of behavior when you have a nation a
system that tolerates
this sort of behavior it encourages
other people to do that
and such a nation is on very shaky
ground
so these are the
fundamental deep-rooted problems that
india is
currently facing
it needs to find ways of dealing with
them such behavior can never be
tolerated
would the chinese ever tolerate
anti-china behavior from a chinese
citizen
i think not
that's why the chinese are a much
stronger state currently compared to
india
and if you look at our ancient wisdom
treatises like the arthashastra etc
there is very clear prescriptions on how
to deal with anti-national
anti-civilizational behavior very clear
prescriptions so i think we need to
hearken back to our ancient wisdom
dump this fake
entire fake system that we have been
left with after the transfer of power
from the british
and we need to
recreate ourselves afresh
if that can be possible so for that we
will need
real leadership
i'm not saying the current leadership is
good or bad or whatever it is not
um
this is not to be interpreted as a
comment about india's current leadership
india is in a specific
situation right now as a specific
position india is economically still a
small nation and therefore india cannot
do certain things that would actually be
good for india at right now
then shopping said the the chinese
statesman think shopping said that when
you are weak and when you are not strong
enough
you keep your head down you bide your
time you hide your capabilities and you
build it towards becoming great again
that's what ding shopping said i think
india will do well
to emulate that and to heed that wisdom
next 5 10 15 years or so just keep your
head down
don't show off your capabilities and
build build build
and once the time is right we can
reunite in india the way we need to
and we can deal with the external
adversaries the way we need to so it's a
question of biding one's time
and building rebuilding the nation
and when the time is that we can
take the necessary steps
in the national interest in the
civilizational interest
in the interest of all indian citizens
that's what needs to happen
all right
let's take some other questions
okay some
[Laughter]
bunty gupta says my views on black lives
matter
and the indian player cricket players
taking a knee before a cricket match
listen black lives matter is a very
valid and legitimate movement
if you know the if you study the history
of america
you will see how
the black the african origin people were
treated the treatment was horrific
inhumane barbaric primitive and brutal
so the
so clearly
they they have been treated in a
horrific manner even today even today
they are second-class citizens of some
kind
in in certain ways in the us
if you are a black person
you are far more likely of being shot by
police
there is racial profiling there's so
much more
so black lives matters matter is
a legitimate and valid
uh movement
but of course we have to also recognize
the fact that it's a political movement
in the us you have two major two major
political parties the republicans
and the democrats
the democrats are very much
pro-blm
and blm doesn't have that much of
support
compared to the democrats
among the republicans and the people who
support the republican party so this is
even this i i i recognize that it's a
very legitimate movement but it's also a
political movement
so if you support this movement in the
us if you're an american if you support
the movement you are making a political
statement in
in a way it's a political statement in
favor in support of the democratic party
and in opposition to the republican
party in a way
right i'm not saying it's right or wrong
or anything it's just an observation as
an outsider
right
now
black lives matter is an american issue
it's an american movement
we certainly can never support racism
racism is abhorrent it is barbaric it's
inhuman
and
we cannot support racism ever
so
now blm has no
context in the indian
uh
socio-cultural milieu
there are no black people who were
marginalized or oppressed in india
right
black people were brought to india some
black people some african origin people
were brought to india as slaves
by the turko arabic
occupiers of
india and their descendants still live
in india today
and they live as indian citizens equal
indian citizens right they have the same
rights as indians as all indians
they are so it's a very small number of
people and they have never faced any
operation
from
the people or the culture of india
so the point is that blm has no
relevance in india
there are no blm issues in india
and it's a political movement in the us
now these indian cricketers they
took a knee in support of blm
which is fine i don't have a problem in
supporting a legitimate movement
but then they can no longer claim that
don't mix cricket and politics don't mix
sport and politics
the
refrain you hear from indian cricketers
all the time is that don't make sport in
politics do not talk about politics this
is a political issue don't ask me we are
sports people we'll talk about support
now what happened
they have made a political statement
here
blm
they can no longer claim that sport and
politics don't mix because they
themselves
brought politics into sport by taking
the knee do they even know what they
were doing
and are there no issues in india that
need their support more than blm
you have a genocide of hindus happening
in bangladesh did any of them say a word
about that
no
you have the kashmiris who have been
expelled the kashmiri hindus who are
living as refugees in their own country
is there a word against against that
that atrocity
no
but blm black lives matter i have
nothing against black lives matter it is
a
valid legitimate movement i support
the the
quest of the of the african-americans
for equal rights
i do
but it is not an indian issue
and if
indian cricketers want to make up a
statement against any oppression or
injustice they should look closer to
home
there are issues happening in our own
neighborhood
whether it is the atrocities against
minorities in pakistan
whether it is atrocities are in
minorities in afghanistan
whether it is the
near genocide of hindus in bangladesh
whether it is what's happened to the
kashmiri hindus and so on and so forth
there is so much
that needs their support
they are very prominent very visible
people
lots of young indians look up to these
cricketers
and they want to support blm which they
don't even know what what it's what it
really is
so i think it's shameful it is extremely
disappointing these people have done
that
right and they have themselves
mixed up
sport
with politics so i think
it would be hypocritical of them now
after this to
to hide behind the statement of don't
mix sport and
politics because they themselves have
politicized this entire thing
and the thing is that this political
posturing and this virtue signaling of
theirs
has unfortunately
interfered with their performance
the way they lost i mean i have nothing
against losing
but the manner in which they lost was
atrocious it was shameful
india had a proud record of always
beating pakistan in world cup encounters
these people
uh
brought that down they broke that that
incredible streak
and the way they lost was was was
shameful
right so i would i would say i would
conclude
by saying to all the youngsters
please choose your heroes wisely
do not hero worship entertainers
cricketers are entertainers
these people are paid crores of rupees
to entertain you
do not hero worship entertainers
find real heroes
to emulate real heroes
these people have not sacrificed
anything
they haven't sacrificed their lives they
haven't sacrificed their blood their
families or anything to build up this
nation
right
so treat this as entertainment and
entertainment only do not hero worship
them do not treat them as idols to
emulate
that's all i would like to conclude this
question this answer by saying all right
good question
smith says how do we how can we
differentiate between distorted history
and real history experience read a lot
use your intelligence ask a lot of
questions question everything
read history from lots of different
perspectives and slowly slowly you will
start getting an understanding of what
is right and what is
clearly wrong
after some time after you read a lot you
will develop an instinct a sixth sense
which will tell you
when something is a distorted piece or a
fabricated piece of history
so that's the only way there's you can
either read a lot and trust your own
judgment or you need to find somebody
who is trustworthy and who can inform
you so it is all up to you and your
judgment your wisdom your intelligence
to do that right
that's that's all i can say about this
it's it it takes a lot of reading and
experience to to reach that stage
otherwise what will be the impact on the
world if iran gets nuclear weapons what
will be the impact or effect on india
please also throw a light on the
government of in of iran kingdom of
saudi arabia and iran which is better
that's a whole lot of questions in one
see iran is
if you look at the history
of iran since 1979 which is the islamic
revolution when ayatollah khomeini came
to power by ousting the shah of iran
muhammad
the so-called iranian revolution
so after that iran has taken a certain
political and geopolitical trajectory
iran has been very active
and vigorous in pursuing its
interests beyond its borders it has a
very
active uh
active what do you call it
spy agency
intelligence agency they have
agents
across us across west asia
they have a very significant presence in
iraq right now iraq is i think at least
40 percent shia
and those uh
that
particular demographic will be pro iran
so they have so the iranians have a
significant presence there
right their intelligence services and
all that
uh they also are active in
in syria
they are active in afghanistan to some
extent
and they are also
active in yemen and they are
[Applause]
they are assisting the houthis i believe
in their struggle against the
saudi arabian regime and so on so the
iranians
are very active in that manner beyond
their borders they are not shy from
projecting power beyond their borders
and they are an expansionist
regime
they seek to
in a way recreate the ancient persian
empire
the persian empire of nadersha
who
perpetrated a bloodbath in delhi
so they want to recreate the persian
empire
and imagine if this
regime were to get nuclear weapons do
you think they will behave the same way
they behave right now
hell no
it would be a threat to everybody in
this neighborhood
it would be a threat to pakistan the
iranians are not particularly friendly
towards pakistan
it would be a threat for india it would
be a threat for the saudis it would be a
threat for everybody it would be threat
for israel as well
iran should not get nuclear weapons it
is in no way beneficial for india
for iran to get nuclear weapons
the iranians are not a very
friendly nice power okay so
so the effect on india would be a
dangerous
nuclear-armed terrorist state of sorts
in the neighborhood
you could look upon iran as a terrorist
state they have undertaken terrorist
activities
in various parts of the neighborhood
they even handed over an indian
citizen
a businessman
to the pakistanis so they are not
friendly towards india you know who it
is right kulbhushan jadhav he is an
indian businessman
he was an indian businessman who was
working
in iran
in the iranian part of balochistan i
think it was chabahar where was it
somewhere there
and they allowed the pakistani isi
to kidnap an indian citizen a
businessman from iranian soil and take
him into pakistan so iran is in no way a
friend of india remember that
it is almost like a terrorist state in
many ways like pakistan they indulge in
proxy wars with various other states and
so on
so it would not be a good thing for the
neighborhood for the step-by-step for
the stability of the neighborhood and
the security of the neighborhood if the
iranians were to acquire nuclear weapons
not a good deal
uh ksa and iran which is better i
from india's perspective i think we have
better relations with the saudis
than with the iranians as of right now
so maybe the the saudis are better
partners for india on the geopolitical
arena than the parsis the iranians right
dhungar
alive today that's a lovely question in
case you don't know what titanob was let
me let me show you
titanoboa was an ancient serpent
a very old ancient snake let me share
the screen with you and
show you what this
wonderful animal looked like
here we go
so if you search google for titanoboa
you get this so it's in very it's a very
large snake that lived
in
central and south america
about 60 million years ago
it could grow up to 12 or 13 meters long
and reach a weight of 1.13
tons
enormous enormous
serpent as you can see
that's how large
this snake was
huge monstrous snake currently the
largest snake that exists on the planet
is the anaconda which is again in
southern america a very large snake in
itself but this one was even larger
enormous maybe the largest snake that
ever existed
this gives you an idea of how large
or how large this animal was
so if it was alive today i think we
would have rendered it extinct because
humans are the apex
predator
on our planet
the most dangerous predator
on earth is the human being we may not
be enormous huge powerful physically
imposing in all
but we are the most intelligent species
and we are a war like predatory species
we have wiped out more species than
anybody else if the titan or boy was
alive today we would have eaten him to
death i'm sure our ancestors
right
so yeah it would not pose a threat to us
unless
we would venture out in some places and
so on but it would not be a problem for
us at all and the reason why this engine
snake went extinct is because it was so
large it was so large it needed to hunt
enormous animals and eat a lot just to
stay alive and as the climate change and
all it was it became impossible for it
to find sufficient
prey
to sustain itself and that's why slowly
this this particular
species of snake
of python
died out and went extinct
uh enormous animals are unsustainable
over long periods periods of time we had
this enormous shark called the megalodon
which also went extinct we had
enormous uh
sloths called megatherium
which
our ancestors humans drove extinct let
me show you what that looked like
let me share that just a second
so there was this species of sloth
called megatherium which which
which was alive during
at the same time as humans
and our ancestors
ancient humans
hunted this down and drove it extinct it
was an enormous enormous
species as you can see
so our ancestors i'm not sure where this
thing lived did it live in asia or did
it live
yes this animal lived in south america
uh let me repeat that wikipedia is not a
reliable source of information but it's
the quickest source of information so
you can get a rough idea about things
from this website but you should not
rely upon it especially when it comes to
history and culture
so megatherium was a
giant sloth that was endemic to south
america
and it was wiped out
by
humans
by humans who lived there so yeah so so
my point is that no matter how large an
animal is we will find a way to wipe it
out that's just the nature of humans
right
so titanoboa would not have posed any
genuine threat to us we would have dealt
with it comfortably
okay let's take some more interesting
questions
chaitanya chaturvedi says even if we
don't believe in the aryan invasion
theory should we call ourselves as
aryans
so the word arya is a sanskrit word
which means civilized
or superior
you can interpret it in a number of ways
but it essentially means
a cultured refined and civilized
person
now it was an
adjective it is something that you would
ascribe to a person who has good
manners and a good upbringing and
a civilized
uh behavior right
but when our distant ancestors moved out
of india and wealth went to other
geographies for instance
when
our ancestors when ancient indians
migrated westwards and went to persia
and settled in persia the
the parshu parshu people who named
the parshwa people the partial people
who gave
this land their name and called it
persia
so these people
once they settled in persia they used
this term arya
as an ethnic term
as an ethnic self-identification as a
term of ethnic self-identification
so they
interpret treated this word as something
that
denoted their ethnicity
so that was the first time that this
word this term arya was used as an
ethnic term and not just as an
adjective and later the europeans tried
to steal it from us
the germans said that we are the aryans
we are the aryan peoples the north
europeans are the real aryans and all
that and that is uh the genesis to some
extent of the aryan invasion theory this
european supremacist theory eurocentric
theory that everything good came from
europe and not from india which is
completely incorrect as i have
spoken about in the past
so clearly it's not about believing or
not believing in the orientation theory
it's about the
it's about the fact that
evidence data
doesn't agree with this theory
all the evidence all the data points to
the fact that
if there was an invasion
it happened out of india if there were
migrations they happened out of india
india was the source the origin of the
genetics and the languages there are the
indo-european genetics and languages so
it's not about believing and not
behaving it's about the
data doesn't is not consistent with this
theory
so should we call ourselves aryans well
if any
particular ethnicity is to be called the
aryans it is the iranians and the
indians the indians and the iranians
nobody else
nobody else can be called aryans
so it's up to you whether you want to
call yourself yourself an aryan or not
all indians and all iranians
can legitimately call themselves
aryans
if you call yourself an iron if i call
myself an aryan it is it would not be
an incorrect
statement
right
but in india we have never used this
term as an ethnic identifier it was
simply a word that made that meant
civilized
and uh
yeah civilized essentially
so if you wish to call yourself an aryan
it would not be incorrect by any means
okay let's take some more questions
i have
excuse me address this question in the
past
is jainism older than sarat and dharma
how is it related to surrounding dharma
historically
jainism jaina dharma both the dharma
etc they are all part of the larger
dharmic traditions
they are all
part of sanatana dharma
jainism how old it is it may actually be
as old as the entire dharmic tradition
we don't quite know according to
jain according to uh the jaina world
view
vardaman mahavira was the 24th
tirthankar he was a near contemporary of
gotham buddha which places him about two
and a half thousand years before today
and he was the 24th tirthankar
of jainism which means there were 23
before him so it goes back possibly
several thousand years we don't know
so we can't really tell how old jainism
is it is clearly a very ancient
uh
school of philosophy it's a
philosophical school of thought just
like both the dharma even in buddhism
even in both dharma
gautam buddha was just one in a long
line of buddhas and there will be future
buddhas as well
so the the thing is that jainism is not
a separate religion it is just part of
the dharmic
traditions
it is one of the dharmic schools of
thought
so
this entire narrative of
of
dividing
the indian traditions into separate
religions is a colonial
project
they have tried to divide and rule us
so they so today indians believe that
jainism is a separate religion buddhism
is a separate religion sikhism is a
separate religion and hinduism is a
separate religion
that is a colonial western view
it is all the same
this is all part of dharma itself that's
it
so
it is not related to sanatana dharma it
is
a part of sanatana dharma
that's all i can say about this
right let's take some more questions
[Laughter]
what uh okay this is the question by
shivam goyal i'm laughing because i
think i've taken this before but why not
let's address this again
what according to you is the origin of
the rajputs and how much water does the
claim of theory that their descendants
of shakka tribes of central asia
we don't know what is the origin of
rajputs
because our historians have not
addressed this question at all
there are only speculations
and hypotheses but there is no
you need
detailed research into the lineages of
each rajput clan
to try and understand what is the real
origin of the rajputs the term rajput is
a very recent term if you look at the
entire timeline of indian history
the various aristocratic and warrior
clans
that were in existence in the 11th 12th
century or thereabouts or later
they came to be known as the rajya
putras
which eventually became
known as rajputs
so these were royal clans aristocratic
plants warrior clans
so this term is a more recent term they
were not called rajputs 1500 years ago
even though the same clans were
to some some of these these clans were
still were already in existence right
and then there is a question of what is
the who are the guru gurujas and who are
the rajputs and all listen these terms
don't matter we are all indians
we all have the same origins
uh are the rajmu's descendants of
scheithians from central asia
i don't quite think so there is no
evidence that proves this
there is no evidence that corroborates
such a claim
we do know that the skittions did invade
india they settled down
in india they assimilated harmoniously
with the people of india because they
were the same ethnicity and they're the
same culture and they're a very similar
language
so the skittions were essentially the
same people as the indians they were
able to just harmoniously blend into
india into the indian population if you
look at the genetics of the people of
western and northern india you don't see
it you don't see any difference
from the genetics of other parts of
india they're more or less the same
we know that ketians did settle down
in these parts of india
so yes it is clear that some
some people
in these regions would have skin
ancestry some people may even have some
fractional greek ancestry
and yet the genetics shows that they are
all indians just like everybody else
right
so
i am not quite sure how correct this
theory is that some rajputs may be
descendants of sketians so there may
certainly be some sketian blood
in the rajputs there may also be kushan
blood in the rajputs again the kushans
were not foreigners some people comment
on my videos and say that the questions
were horns or the questions were turks
they were not
they were the same ethnicity the same
genetics as indians
if you look at the tarim basin
mummies
in
north of the himalayas they all have the
r1a haplogroup which is an indian
patrilineal lineage right
and that is where the questions came
from from the tarim basin river region
the so-called xinjiang region of
present-day
chinese occupied whatever that part of
the land is
so yes rajputs and northern indians and
western indians will have some skit
ancestry they will have some kushan
ancestry but they were genetically and
culturally and religiously and
ethnically indian
so i think we need to stop looking at
foreign ancestry for all ours or all of
us
even that foreign ancestry eventually
came from india
so
but to answer your question
we still don't have
clarity
on the actual origins of the rajput
lineages
because we have lost our records of
history in the destruction of our
universities and today's historians have
not
have have deliberately
not studied this issue
because the rajputs are
where india's protectors nobody's
spilled more blood in the defense of
india than the rajputs right so it is
best for india's historians to keep this
part of india's history neglected and
marginalized
so that's what we can say right now you
know that's that's all that's what we
know
which is very little unfortunately
samarth asks if the majority of the
harappan people lived on the banks of
the saraswati river why are the people
of india referred to as hindus which is
a term derived from the indus river
good question good very nice i like it
so what we find is that if we look at
the
uh
if we look at the archaeological sites
that are known to exist in the sapta
sindhu region
which is the geography of the saraswati
and sindhu
river system
then there are more than 1500
archaeological sites on the dried on on
the banks of the dried riverbed of the
saraswati we know it it's there they
have not been explored they have not
been excavated but we know they are
there
more than 1 500 unexplored
archaeological sites on the banks of the
saraswati which is more than on the
banks of any other river system because
this was the major biggest
river of this region
so
if this is the case clearly this is the
case so then why are
the people of india called hindus which
is derived from the indus river
well the first
people
from outside india
to call
indians hindus where the parsis the
persians the parshwa the descendants of
the rigvedic
clan
so these
parshwa people they went out of india
westwards they settled in persia
and
the land was named after them persia
power parshwa all that
and slowly slowly slowly they drifted
away from indian culture and
civilization they they adopted this new
religion called zoroastrianism which is
another polytheistic religion but
somewhat different from
from india's ancient uh from their own
ancestral religion and so on
and their language started changing
slowly i spoke about blood chronology in
the past in this episode itself
about an hour ago so language changes
so their ancient persian language was
very similar to sanskrit but
pronunciations were different in some
cases so saw became ha
so the sindhu river
they called it the hindu river because
saw became her in their language
[Music]
but
by the time they started calling india
calling sindhu hindu by that time the
saraswati had already dried out
the saraswati dried out sometime around
1500 bce
so then the memory of the saraswati for
these people it slowly faded away
and then the only major river in this
region which was left the biggest river
was the sindhu
which they called the hindu
so then they slowly started i guess
calling the entire region as a sindhu
region of the hindu region and that's
how this
term hindu became associated with the
people of this region and then when the
greeks came to india they came via
persia
so they had already heard about this
region called hindu and they
most likely started associating the name
with the people
and that's how they started calling
indians hindus and then the same thing
was
you find with the arabs and the turks
and so on
so when these foreigners
uh started using this name by the time
the saraswati had already dried out
in this region
and that's why
only the indus remained as the major
river
and that's how this name was
uh was was put forth
so i hope that answers your question
okay let's take some
more
questions
one asks is it true that ravindranath
thakur
wrote jana ganamana the indian national
anthem for the british king george the
fifth well there are some people
who say that it was not for the british
king it was for lord
krishna if you
read the entire text of this poem
then
it appears that it was actually in in uh
in praise of lord krishna
so the adinaya
is lord krishna that's what some people
claim
i am not quite sure about that
i still have my doubts
but some very prominent people
do claim that it was actually in in in
praise of lord krishna so i think that
you know
this needs to be examined in more detail
i i
am a little doubtful about this claim i
think that
we need to examine this in more detail
i'm not quite convinced
okay let's take some more question
okay sid asks
how will the kashmir dispute be resolved
what are the measures that are needed
see the kashmir dispute is not about
kashmir
if india was to give kashmir all to
pakistan you think the pakistanis will
become india's friends
no
they will still remain india's enemies
the problem is not kashmir
the problem is
pakistan as long as india exists
the pakistanis will never be happy
even if india hands over kashmir to
pakistan they will never be happy they
will continue
their terrorist activities against india
they will continue their anti-india
activities
so the problem
the root of the problem whenever you
have a problem you have to do a root
cause analysis
the
solution to peace between india and
pakistan is not handing over kashmir to
pakistan
the root of the problem is the pakistani
mindset itself
the root of the problem is the nation
state of pakistan and the army and the
isi
so what needs to happen how can the
kashmir problem be resolved what are the
measures that are needed
it's very simple pakistan needs to cease
to exist as a nation pakistan needs to
be fragmented into components
smaller components
pok and gilgit balthasar need to be
reunited with india
punjab needs to become an independent
nation pakistani punjab pakistani punjab
needs to become an independent nation
the
the the pashtun parts of pakistan north
west frontier private etc need to be
reunited with afghanistan
sindh needs to become independent
balochistan needs to be independent
and then we can have good relations with
all of these
uh independent countries the pakistani
army needs to be
dealt with
appropriately
the isi needs to be
dealt with appropriately i have i i
genuinely
have nothing against the people of
pakistan they are equally victims they
live horrible lives
they themselves are oppressed whether
they know it or not i genuinely don't
have any anything against them
if they if this happens it should
it should we should try to do it
peacefully
without
too much
resorting to
military violence and all that
so
the people should not suffer but this is
a problem for india we need to resolve
it
we need to make this happen
in the next five to ten years at most
we cannot allow this problem to go on
forever the problem that mr nehru and mr
gandhi created right with the
uh
on the agenda of the british
so this needs to be resolved and the
only solution is the
balkanization of pakistan which needs to
happen in the next five to ten years
like i said india's economy is growing
when india reaches a certain stage in
its economy india's military strength
will also be measurable in proportion to
that and when the time is right the
right actions need to be taken
so i think it's simply a matter of time
i think we should not wait for more than
5 or 10 years i think 10 years at most
to resolve this problem then we can deal
with the real problem which is
which is in the north
right let's take
some more questions
sanskriti says i don't know how someone
can demand
archaeological evidence of a text
written thousands of years ago as paper
and other writing materials cannot
survive for so long
well sanskriti you are absolutely right
paper
is perishable
and especially in india's climate
especially in the past
when the monsoon was much more
heavy
much heavier than it is today
so the climate the temperature etc the
warm temperature the humid climate etc
it's not conducive
to the uh
preservation of organic material tissues
paper etc these things will crumble and
disappear and disintegrate
so it is obviously
not
right to expect
such materials to last that long
but it works for these people from for
the communists for the for the
eurocentric historic et cetera who like
to say that you know there is no
evidence you guys have no written
history and so on nothing has survived
because nothing ever existed and so on
so yeah they demand archaeological
evidence and because we have not even
done any archaeology in the past 70
years nothing significant so we don't
have much archaeological evidence that
proves certain things
that corroborate certain
events of our history from the distant
past that are still remembered in our
texts and in our collective memory and
therefore they say that all these things
are just myths
and they never happened
so here's a question for these
historians
where is the archaeological evidence
for alexander the greek
show me one piece of archaeological
evidence that proves this guy existed
we don't have his tomb
we don't have his bones we don't have
his remains
we don't have any
evidence from
archaeology that proves this guy ever
existed
and there are no contemporary texts
from the time when he is supposed to
have existed
there are only three
greek texts that are near
contemporaneous with alexander's
supposed existence
and
western historians have written
thousands of books about alexander on
the basis of just three greek texts
so that is the kind of duplicity and
dual standards you find among historians
on the one hand
they claim this guy existed without any
real evidence that he actually existed
on the other hand we have
such
ancient texts that have that have been
preserved over thousands of years
and they still dispute our claims that
our his our
our recorded history of these ancient
events
so it is the
it is a clear uh
instance of double standards so what
needs to happen is we need to start
approaching our history from our own
perspective we need to
create our own academic ecosystem of of
genuine historians young historians
we need to to fund them to support them
to give them institutional and
governmental support and empower them to
uncover our true history we need to have
our own
journals of history where our research
is published without seeking the
approval of western historians when we
start developing this
this entire ecosystem
academic ecosystem academic system and
so on then we will regain our
self-respect and we will be able to
properly start documenting our history
and uncovering more history
so that's what needs to happen
anonymous asks how japan which is much
smaller than india has an economy much
better than us
well that is the big question isn't it i
mean it's very simple to answer
nehru
sorry i should not say nehru i should
say sri jawaharlal nehru the great prime
minister of india
that is the answer
see when india gained
its supposed independence in the
transfer of power from the british to
these to the congress party
india was in a much better state than
japan
japan had been
nuked twice the entire country had been
bombed to dust by the americans
the country was
in a disastrous state of shambles the
entire economy was broken the nation was
in ruins
india had
everything the british had built with
our money
the india had a working railway india
had institutions and so on
so india was in a much better position
than japan or even china at the time
and then what happened is that shri
jawaharlal nehru happened
he was appointed the prime minister of
india by mr gandhi and other people
in the british
and he proceeded to strangle india's
economy
until the time he died
so he imposed his version of fabian
socialism on india he stifled india's
economic
growth he imposed this bureaucratic raj
that licensed raj and whatever else you
call it
and
it led to the nehemiah rate of growth
two to three percent per year
the japanese
rebuilt the japanese came under american
occupation
which they still are under
but they rebuilt their economy
and they rebuilt their nation
and they did all the right things the
things that mr nehru should have done
but never did so the japanese in a few
years and a few decades raced ahead of
india ahead of china
and they became an economic superpower
in the 1980s they were second only to
the americans
so it's all about leadership it's all
about doing the right things
it's all about having the right vision
and
implementing the right programs
nehru shri nehru
was a socialist he was in love with the
soviet model of socialism even that he
did not implement properly
because the soviets were able to
industrialize the country
their country using their means of
marxism and socialism and all that
the vietnam is the chinese also
implemented such methods of social of
social
socialist economics and all that
and that also worked to some extent
mr nero could not even do that properly
so
it's about the leadership
which which uh strangled india india's
economy and india's people for such a
long time
reforms were not done until 1992. and
that too it was india was forced to do
these reforms it's not like the the
indian government wanted to do reforms
at the time but india was left with no
option in 92. so
in a nutshell that's why japan did so
much better than india even south korea
did so much better than india even south
korea was destroyed
in the korean war in the 1950s even they
were able to come out of that
singapore was a third world dump
when it became independent
in just one generation they became a
first world country it's possible if you
have the right leaders
india had the wrong leader
right
what else do we have
how much is the book sapiens by
uh
harare
biased
i haven't read the book
i haven't read it so i can't tell you
uh
i have it
i have many books
that are waiting to be read
i don't have the time
i have a
a reading list that
is more than 100 books strong right now
so yeah
so i haven't read it yet hopefully
someday in the next couple of years i
may read it if i find the time
all right
let me take one more question
vishal says if tibet is liberated in the
next 15 to 20 years
should we integrate it in nepal with
india
considering india will be the super
power income in decades listen there is
no guarantee that india will be a
superpower in the coming decades there
is no guarantee tibet will be liberated
in the next 15 20 years we would like to
see that happen we would like to see
both things happen we would like to see
india become a superpower in the next
two decades at most we would like to see
tibet be liberated in the next 20 years
15 20 years
i would like to see that happen but
there is no guarantee that will happen
we need
the right leaders in place we need the
right succession
a leader has a certain amount of time
that he or she can lead the country then
they have to pass on the baton to the
next person it is up to india's
population india's voters to vote the
right party the right people in
otherwise will start going backwards so
it's all if ifs and buts but
if tibet is liberated in the next 15 20
years should we integrate it with india
in nepal
i think india should continue to have
i think india should certainly in
reintegrate nepal with india
in the near to long term near to medium
term
maybe 20 30 years because nepal has
always been part of india civilization
listen my nepalese friends
please don't hate me for saying this
nepal and india are the same people the
same civilization same culture same
everything right now there is a
communist party in power in nepal i know
what they are teaching the students so
that students are getting brainwashed
so there is a significant anti-india
sentiment in nepal right now we are
different we are the birthplace of
buddhism lord buddha all that come on
guys
we are the same people
so yeah nepal should be reintegrated
with india
when the time is right
maybe the next 20 years or so
if tibet is liberated from china
india needs to have an open border with
tibet
if the things if the situation is right
so the way we have an open border with
nepal right now
had tibet never come under chinese
control i think india would have had a
similar open border with tibet
because tibet is
an extremely friendly country
tibetan culture indian culture are the
same tibetan culture is a local
manifestation of indian culture we have
the same culture the same
civilization the same beliefs the same
values the same principles
we may be different ethnicities but we
have we are the same civilization so
india and tibet would have had an open
border had tibetan been free
if tibet is liberated once the chinese
influence goes away once it is
once tibet is totally secure we should
have an open border with them we should
not try to rein to integrate tibet with
india
because tibet was never part of india
tibet has always been a neighboring
uh region north of the himalayas
the most we should do is reintegrate the
region of the kailash monster
region with india that that that
certainly belongs
in india it is one of the of our holiest
and most
sacred places but tibet we should not
try to integrate it within india we can
have an open border
no possible no visas that sort of policy
the kind of policy we have with nepal
right now
uh so yeah so that's what should happen
in the hypothetical case that tibet is
liberated in the next
15 20 years
all right
abhishek asks how do you define great
leadership
that is a very
profound question there is no one
sentence definition
of great leadership
at its very core
leadership is service
leadership is selfless service
leadership is service without any
expectation of personal
gain
so that is leadership but that is not
great leadership
great leadership is doing
is is
is taking
your constituency your country forward
in the right direction despite all the
enormous
problems that it inevitably faces
so
that is a very big topic it's not
something you can define in a few
minutes in a few sentences
but just understand this much for now
leadership is
nothing but service
and it is service that is selfless
service that
without any expectation of personal
benefit or gain
so that's what i can say right now so we
will conclude this session with this
question about leadership
thank you for your all your questions
thank you for watching thank you for
your participation
i will see you tomorrow tomorrow we have
a live video chat session
on sunday
so i will see you all then all right
until then take care
and thank you very much i will see you
tomorrow bye